<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The voluntarie conuersion and seuerall recantations, of foure great learned men, professed fryers in sundry monasteries of Fraunce, from the errours of idolatrie and poperie, to the true religion established in the Reformed Church. 1. Master Iohn Le Vager, a priest in the Romane Church, conuerted at Mauns, Ianuary 6. 2. Master Iohn Forent, a fryer Carmelite, in the Court of Morthemard, conuerted in the Reformed Church of Poictiers, Iune, 9. 3. Master Denis Boucher, a Franciscane fryer, in the couent of Noisy, neere Paris, conuerted in the Reformed Church of Paris, Iuly. 6. 4. Master Daniell Dusert,  Franciscan fryer at Mello, conuerted in the Church of Mello, December, 22. All conuerted this last yeare, 1603. as their seuerall discourses following at large doe testifie, vnder their owne hands. Truely translated, out of the French printed copies.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 101 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B12171</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5650</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114587</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849812</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849812</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177893</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B12171)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177893)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1268:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The voluntarie conuersion and seuerall recantations, of foure great learned men, professed fryers in sundry monasteries of Fraunce, from the errours of idolatrie and poperie, to the true religion established in the Reformed Church. 1. Master Iohn Le Vager, a priest in the Romane Church, conuerted at Mauns, Ianuary 6. 2. Master Iohn Forent, a fryer Carmelite, in the Court of Morthemard, conuerted in the Reformed Church of Poictiers, Iune, 9. 3. Master Denis Boucher, a Franciscane fryer, in the couent of Noisy, neere Paris, conuerted in the Reformed Church of Paris, Iuly. 6. 4. Master Daniell Dusert,  Franciscan fryer at Mello, conuerted in the Church of Mello, December, 22. All conuerted this last yeare, 1603. as their seuerall discourses following at large doe testifie, vnder their owne hands. Truely translated, out of the French printed copies.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Richard Bradocke, for W. Iones [2], dwelling at the signe of the Gun, neere Holborne Conduit: and are to be solde by W. Aspley, in Paules Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1604.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Clarification regarding W. Jones from STC.</note>
                  <note>Leaves F2-3 cropped at head, with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Protestant converts --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177893:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177893:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE VOLVNTARIE CONVERSION, AND SEVERALL RECANTATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, of foure great learned men, <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Fryers in ſundry Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of Fraunce,</hi> FROM THE ERROVRS OF IDOLATRIE and Poperie, to the true Religion eſtabliſhed in the <hi>Reformed Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Maſter <hi>Iohn Le Vager,</hi> a Prieſt in the <hi>Romane</hi> Church, conuerted at <hi>Mauns, Ianuary</hi> 6.</item>
               <item>2. Maſter <hi>Iohn Forent,</hi> a Fryer Carmelite, in the Couent of <hi>Morthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mard,</hi> conuerted in the Reformed Church of <hi>Poictiers, Iune,</hi> 9.</item>
               <item>3. Maſter <hi>Denis Boucher,</hi> a Franciſcane Fryer, in the Couent of <hi>Noiſy,</hi> neere <hi>Paris,</hi> conuerted in the Reformed Church of <hi>Paris, Iuly.</hi> 6.</item>
               <item>4. Maſter <hi>Daniell Duſert,</hi> a Franciſcan Fryer at <hi>Mello,</hi> conuerted in the Church of <hi>Mello, December,</hi> 22.</item>
            </list>
            <p>¶ All conuerted this laſt yeare, 1603. as their ſeuerall diſcourſes following at large doe teſtifie, vnder their owne hands.</p>
            <p>Truely tranſlated, out of the French printed Copies.</p>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>Richard Bradocke,</hi> for <hi>W. Iones,</hi> dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at the ſigne of the Gun, neere Holborne Conduit: and are to be ſolde by <hi>W. Aſpley,</hi> in <hi>Paules</hi> Church-yard. 1604.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:177893:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177893:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS WORTHILIE RESPECTED KINDE FRIEND, Maſter <hi>George Gibſon,</hi> Citizen and <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant Taylor of London.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N regard of your many kindneſſes, and no other meanes remaining in mee of requitall, except ſuch as my condition alloweth: I ſend you this ſmall labour of mine, being the ſeuerall conuerſions of foure learned men, from Popiſh errour and blinde ſuperſtition. The fame of them hath beene farre extended, in regard of the learned handling of each diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe: which, vpon conſideration, I am ſure good iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments both haue, and will confeſſe no leſſe. I deſire you to accept my good will, and burie all defects in the honeſtie of mine intent toward you, till better occaſion may afford me a larger meaſure of loue on your behalfe. This ſhould haue been acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panied with another excellent Treatiſe, of a great Ducheſſes conuerſion in the kingdome of <hi>France,</hi> a learned Epiſtle of hers to her Lord and huſband, declaring her ſouls high comfort in her forſaking Idolatry, and the maine Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radoxes of Popery very learnedly diſcouered: but wanting
<pb facs="tcp:177893:3"/> leaſure, in regard of other very ſerious imployments, I am enforced to let it reſt till more apt opportunitie. But I hope within short time to perfect it: which (then) shall helpe to ſupply what wanteth in this toward you. Till when, as heretofore, ſo shall I ſtill remaine your poore wel-wiſhing friend, any way by you to be vſed or commanded.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:177893:3"/>
            <head>A PROFESSION OF FAITH, MADE IN THE reformed Church of MAVNS, the ſixt day <hi>of</hi> Ianuary, 1603. <hi>by Master</hi> IOHN LE VAGER, ſometimes a Prieſt in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it is vndoubtedly true, that God moſt powerfully (by his infinite goodneſſe) hath cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vs all to the knowledge of his holy name, to be his people and his Church, whereon on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he hath beſtowed the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of his mercies, and out of which there is no ſaluation at all: ſo certainly, if wee be deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of this goodneſſe, and would participate of his bleſſings and mercies, it behooueth vs to trauaile and ſtudy, in the ſearch of this Church, to ioyne and incorporate our ſelues into the ſame. And therefore let vs not imitate the heretique EVTICHVS, who ſaide; <hi>That as he had learned of his Fathers, and beleeued in the Faith wherein he</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Concil. Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. Act. 2.</note> 
               <hi>was borne, euen ſo hee deſired to dye.</hi> Or as AVXENTIVS the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:177893:4"/> 
               <hi>Arrian,</hi> who ſaid: <hi>That as he had learned from his infancie, ſo</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hillarius in 1. Epiſt. ad Aux.</note> 
               <hi>hee beleeued, and would doe ſtill.</hi> Or as the Iewes, thus ſpeaking to <hi>Ieremie: Wee and our Fathers haue done thus.</hi> Or as our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries <note place="margin">Ier. 44. 17.</note> at this day doe, who tels vs, that thus our fathers li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and beleeued. To all which, God thus anſwered by his Prophet <hi>Ezechiel: Walke not yee in the ordinances of your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, neither obſerue their waies, nor defile your ſelues with their</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 20. 18. 19.</note> 
               <hi>Idols. I am the Lord your God, walke in my Statutes, and keepe my iudgements, and doe them. Search the Scriptures,</hi> ſaith our <note place="margin">Iohn. 5. 39.</note> Sauiour Chriſt to the Iewes. And in the Goſpel of <hi>S. Matthew</hi> alſo, foretelling vs of the euil times which now are come vpon vs, he doth aduertiſe vs, that there ſhall be a deſolation and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolt in his Church, and <hi>that many falſe Prophets ſhall ariſe, who</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Math. 24. 11.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall come diſguiſed in ſheepes cloathing:</hi> as now adaies wee ſee the like doone, by our Monkes, Capuchines and Ieſuites, who diſguiſe themſelues in habits of ſimplicitie, of pouerty, of ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie &amp; humilitie, and leaue their owne common garments, the better to ſeduce &amp; beguile poore ſimple people, who ſuffer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeues willingly to be led, by their outward appearances, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the example of the ancient hypocritical Phariſies, <hi>with their Philacteries</hi> and outward ceremonies. <note place="margin">Math. 23. 5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>We haue a further admonition yet, that when wee ſee this <note place="margin">Math. 24. 5.</note> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion amongſt falſe Prophets, they wil ſay, <hi>Heere is Chriſt; others, there is Chriſt,</hi> as theſe diſſemblers now vſe to doe, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: He is heere vnder the Cabinet, in our faire guilded Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, where he yet workes ſtrange miracles. See heer the Iewes <note place="margin">Falſe miracles among the Fryers in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, in Italy, and elſwhere. Math. 24 16.</note> Launce that pearced his pretious ſide, it is heere on this Altar: See heere a handkercher or napkin, coloured with his bloode. But I ſay, that God commandeth vs in this confuſion of decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Prophets, not to beleeue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but <hi>that we ſhould fly to the mountaines.</hi> By which mountaines, he inſinuateth vnto vs, that we ſhould withdrawe, &amp; make diligent ſearch in the ſacred Scriptures, on the foundations whereof hee hath builded his Church. So doth ſaint <hi>Iohn Chryſoſtome</hi> inſtruct, ſpeaking v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon that place, <hi>When yee ſhal ſee the abhomination of deſolation, ſtanding in the holy place:</hi> the Lord commandeth vs (ſaith he) <note place="margin">Math. 24. 15. <hi>Chriſoſt. in ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re imperfect.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that al Chriſtians, ſuch as deſire to holde a firmneſſe in true faith
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:177893:4"/> ſhould retyre themſelues to the holy Scriptures: for if they goe to any place elſe, they will be ſcandalized and periſh, as not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding what the true Church is,</hi> and ſo may eaſily fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the abhomination of deſolation, crept into the holy places of the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Origen</hi> in like manner ſaith, <hi>Thoſe ſoules that are ignorant of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Origen in Mat. C. 24.</note> 
               <hi>the word of trueth and iuſtice, and by that occaſion are eaſily ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, cannot abide without ſeduction, at the verie ſight of the abhomination of deſolation, in the holy place.</hi> Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> likewiſe ſaith, <hi>At the comming of the Meſſias, the people that had ſlept vnder their teachers enſtructions, went to the mountains</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hierom. in Prophet. C. 3.</note> 
               <hi>of the Scriptures, and there found the old mountaines, the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of the Prophets, and the mountaines of the new Teſtament.</hi> And euen as fleſh and bloud hath not reuealed Ieſus Chriſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, but the Father which is in heauen: ſo ought wee not to ſeeke for his Church, according to our corporal ſenſe, but with the eyes of faith in the holy Scriptures, wherein God himſelfe ſpeakes vnto vs, and teacheth vs the will and league hee hath made with his people, which wee ſhoulde alwaies haue before our eyes, on our foreheades, and in our handes, to meditate thereon both day and night, to accompliſh the ſame on our behalfe.</p>
            <p>As concerning my ſelfe, I acknowledge and confeſſe, that I haue beene trained vp in the <hi>Romane</hi> Church, and haue fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the errours and ſuperſtitions therein vſed: being cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <note place="margin">His proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning himſelf, and the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors wherein he hath liued long.</note> only by cuſtome, regarde of antiquitie, and the goodly out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhew deliuered. For looking and contemplating it with the eye of fleſh, it appeared to me to be to be the true Church, erec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for perpetuall continuance, defended on all ſides: as being rich, potent, cloathed with golde, purple, and ſcarlet; tryum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phing ouer all her enemies &amp; aduerſaries; adored by the Kings and Princes of the earth; commaunding Emperours, holding dominion ouer many nations, and proſpering euen againſt the children of God, thruſting the true Church into the deſert wilderneſſe: But all this was according to the Prophecie of <hi>S. Iohn</hi> in his <hi>Apocalipſe,</hi> where he at large deſcribeth Antichriſt <note place="margin">Apoc. Chap. 11. &amp; 12.</note> and his <hi>Babilon.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:177893:5"/>
            <p>Now in this perplexitie, in this conflict of opinions, which we daily ſee about the matter of Religion: according to the commandement of God, I conſulted with the diuine Oracle, and withdrewe my ſelfe to the mountaines of holy Scripture. By whoſe teſtimonie, Ieſus Chriſt repulſed the Tempter, and confirmed his Apoſtles after his reſurrection. By them, our Fathers ſtoned all heretiques, and (beſides them) whatſoeuer is ſpoken, is hereſie and execration, although it be an Angell that <note place="margin">Galat. 1. 8.</note> deliuers it, or an Apoſtle, according as Saint <hi>Paule</hi> teacheth vs. <hi>God will haue obedience by them, and not ſacrifice. Hee will not</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut 12. 4. 2 Sam. 15. 22. Math. 15. 6. Iohn. 10. 4. 5.</note> 
               <hi>be ſerued, according to the commandement and traditions of men. He acknowledgeth them to be his, that abide in his worde.</hi> He tels vs alſo, <hi>that ſuch as are of his flocke, doe heare his voice and knowe it, and will not liſten to a ſtrangers.</hi> See heere the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible markes of the true Church indeed. But the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in ſteede of liſtening to this word, and obeying it, in <note place="margin">Of the church of Rome.</note> ſteede of following the kings high way (which is taught vs by the aforeſaid mountaines) reuolts &amp; turnes after her owne waies, following her owne fantaſies, and not the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Lord. And ſo hath quitted her alliance, that wee may iuſtly ſay of her, that which the Prophet ſpake of the holy citie of <hi>Ieruſalem: How is the faithfull citie become an harlot? She was full of equitie, and iuſtice lodged in her: her gold is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into droſſe, and her wine is mingled with water.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt of all, for example, ſhe will needes haue Idols and <note place="margin">Idols and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages.</note> Images, contrarie to the commandement of God; and to ſhift off this ſinne with an excuſe, ſhe gloſſeth a difference between an Idoll and an Image. And yet the prohibition extendeth, Not to make any reſemblance of any thing, <hi>which is in heauen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exod. 20. 4. 5.</note> 
               <hi>neither in the earth beneath, nor in the waters below, to ſerue or worſhip them.</hi> And ſo themſelues doe cut their owne throats; for they ſay, that the Image which they place in their Temple, is the ſimilitude of that ſame partie in heauen aboue. And if there be any difference betweene Idoll and Image, an Image is for ornament repreſented in an hiſtory: an Idoll, that which is propoſed in the Temple to bee worſhipped, euen as their pretended Images are. THOMAS AQVINAS, one of their <note place="margin">Thomas Aquin.</note>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:177893:5"/> greateſt Doctors teſtifieth the ſame, in 3. <hi>Sentent. diſt. 2. That</hi> 
               <note place="margin">in 3. ſentent. Diſt. 2.</note> 
               <hi>the Image ought to be honoured with the ſelfe ſame adoration, as the partie that it repreſenteth.</hi> And in the booke tearmed <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſiones</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deciſio Rotae,</note> 
               <hi>Rotae,</hi> where the queſtion is demanded, to wit; whether the Image in the Image-makers ſhoppe, be to be worſhipped or no: <hi>He anſwers plainely no; for it is expoſed there to publick ſale: but in the Temple it is placed to be worſhipped;</hi> and the ſelfe ſame inſtruction is giuen, by the <hi>C. venerabiles de Conſ. diſt.</hi> 3. <note place="margin">C. Venerabiles de Conſ. diſt. 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Vpon the aforeſaid holy mountaines, we finde but one God onely, to call vpon in our afflictions and neceſſities; And Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe ſaith vnto vs; <hi>Come vnto me all yee that are wearie and heauie laden, and I will eaſe you.</hi> The Church of <note place="margin">Math. 11. 28.</note> 
               <hi>Rome</hi> ſends vs to ſo many hee-Saints and ſhee-Saints, as there be daies in their Calender: and though it be written; <hi>I wil not impart my glorie to any other:</hi> yet dare they communicate, to all ſuch Saints as themſelues haue canonized, the office of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſour or mediatour betweene God and vs, which office is onely proper to Chriſt, and dependeth vpon his eternall ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice made. For as Saint <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith: <hi>He is entred into very hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 9. 24.</note> 
               <hi>to appeare now in the ſight of God for vs. If any ſinne</hi> (ſaith <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 2. 1.</note> ſaint <hi>Iohn) we haue an Aduocate with the Father, euen Ieſus Chriſt the Iuſt.</hi> In like manner, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt, by one onely ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, made once vpon the Croſſe, hath aboliſhed the ſinnes of all</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10 14.</note> 
               <hi>beleeuers for euer:</hi> ſo that there is no further neede of ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, being once made thus perfectly. But the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as if the ſacrifice of Chriſt were imperfect and inſufficient, hath ordained another, for remiſſion of ſinnes both to the dead and <note place="margin">Maſſes for the liuing and the dead.</note> liuing, which they cal the Maſſe: and hath ſubſtituted ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſucceſſours, for the ſacrificing againe of Ieſus Chriſt, as there be Prieſts that vſe to ſay Maſſe. Contrarie to that which is written: <hi>Thou art a Prieſt eternally for euer, after the order of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 7. 21.</note> MELCHISEDEC, not hauing any ſucceſſour at all in his ſacrifice, as the ſame bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>Paule</hi> teacheth vs.</p>
            <p>And ſo in other points of our Religion, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath wholly peruerted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, namely in Chriſts inſtitution of his <note place="margin">Peruerting of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Of Baptiſme.</note> Sacraments. As in Baptiſme, they make an addition thereto, of Oyle, of Salt, and of Spettle, &amp; transferre (by meere mockery)
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:177893:6"/> this holy myſtery to bels, Baptizing them, as if they were of Gods elect, and to be ranked among the faithful. Likewiſe, the holy Supper which Ieſus Chriſt inſtituted, to make a ſerious <note place="margin">Of the Lords Supper.</note> commemoration of his death and paſſion, whereby he purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed eternall life for vs, bearing the curſe of our ſins vpon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and in that reſpect, after his benediction made, he brake the bread, ſaying: <hi>This is my bodie,</hi> to the end we might there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <note place="margin">Luk. 22. 19.</note> be inſtructed, that as bread nouriſheth our bodies, euen ſo his wounded bodie, deliuered vp vnto death for vs, doth nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh our ſoules vnto eternall life, receiuing the ſame by Faith, and as a Sacrament. The Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> of this foode for the ſoule, would make foode for the bodie; teaching, that this was not ſpoken of the bread, which Chriſt held in his hands, when he pronounced thoſe words <hi>(This is my body)</hi> for the bread was then no more bread: but fantaſtically forge certaine accidents without ſubſtance, of <hi>indiuidua vaga;</hi> and ſay, that that is the true bodie of Chriſt, which deſcended into the bowels of the <note place="margin">C. tribus gradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus de conſec. Diſt. 2.</note> earth, <hi>et per aqualiculos in ſeceſſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> And that Rats, Mice, &amp; dogs may eate the bodie of Chriſt: as they teach in their <hi>Cautelae Miſſae,</hi> and <hi>S. Thomas,</hi> and other Scholaſticks, beſide a thouſand other blaſphemies. They ſay alſo, that this propoſition (that the bread is the bodie of Chriſt) is hereticall, and S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Part. 3. de Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt. Quaeſt. 79. Art. 3. Gerſon contra. floretis. 4. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 651.</note> (by conſequent) an hereticke, who ſaith: <hi>That the bread is the bodie of Ieſus Chriſt in the ſacrament.</hi> And by conſequent alſo, Chriſt himſelfe ſhould be an heretique too, who ſaith in Saint <hi>Iohn: The bread that I will giue you is my fleſh.</hi> Thus make they God imperfect in power, becauſe it is impoſſible, that two bodies ſhoulde bee in one ſelfe ſame place, as they ſay.</p>
            <p>I will rehearſe vnto yee, how the ſaide Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> hath gotten together all the auncient hereſies: as that of <hi>Montanus,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. Hiſt. Eccl. 8. Ca. 18.</note> who forbad mariage, and made lawe for faſting: That of <hi>Pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius,</hi> who taught, that we may doe diuerſe meritorious works. The hereſie of the <hi>Euchites</hi> or <hi>Meſſalians,</hi> who vnder the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of praying to God, and liuing in contemplation: liued in idle ſlothfulneſſe, without doing any thing, <hi>deuouring widowes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luk. 20. 47.</note> 
               <hi>houſes, vnder pretext of long praying,</hi> according as Chriſt repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:177893:6"/> the hypocriticall Scribes. Of whome S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writeth, <note place="margin">Auguſt. de ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Monach.</note> 
               <hi>that they pray ſo long, as it is incredible to them that heare them recount them.</hi> And they ſay, that it is not lawfull for Monks, to labour for their owne ſuſtenance, but commend their idleneſſe, and repute them thereby to be preſeruers and keepers of the Goſpell. And <hi>Theodoret</hi> ſpeaking of them, ſaith: <hi>that Failing</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Theod. heretic. Fabul.</note> 
               <hi>at prayers, they ſleepe the greater part of the day,</hi> and ſo are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to doe: the Authour whereof, was one <hi>Simeon Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſaid Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> doth teach vs a purgatorie, with the Paganes: And giue vs <hi>Aqua luſtralis,</hi> which they tearme <note place="margin">Purgatory.</note> 
               <hi>Holy water,</hi> which was the inuention of <hi>Numa Pompilius</hi> the <note place="margin">Holy water.</note> Idolater. They bring in the Pagan and Iewiſhe pompes, in magnificent habits: as Stones, Luminaries and Proceſſions. I conceale the reſt, for breuitie ſake: onely I ſay, that as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath willingly changed the ordinances of God, and of his Sacraments: euen ſo as willingly hath ſhe got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten an other head and huſband, then Ieſus Chriſt, to wit, the Pope, who calleth the ſaid Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> his Spouſe, and <note place="margin">Cap. quoniam de immuni. in 60. C ſunt qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem dicentes cauſ. 2. 5. quaeſt. 1. et ibi gloſſa.</note> guides her according to his owne fantaſie, giuing her new Lawes; and ſaith, hee hath power ſo to doe, <hi>in C. Sunt quidam dicentes.</hi> And the gloſſe approued and allowed by the ſaide Church, ſaith; <hi>That he may diſpenſe againſt God, and againſt his holy Goſpell.</hi> In the doing of which, hee declares himſelfe to bee hee, of whome ſaint <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeakes to the <hi>Theſſaloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: That hee exalteth himſelfe againſt all that is called God.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2. 4,</note>
            </p>
            <p>For, is not this to exalt himſelfe againſt all that is called God, boldly to dare, to change his Lawes and his Goſpell, to adde thereto, or diminiſh thence, as hee ſaith hee hath power to doe, <hi>In C. Ideo. ſſ. erat?</hi> Alſo hee ſaith, that hee is <note place="margin">C. ideo. ſſ. erat.</note> God, <hi>C. ſatis euidenter, Diſt.</hi> 96. And ſo hee makes himſelfe to bee, by the adoration done vnto him, and kiſſing of his Pantofle. Wee may likewiſe beholde his Monkes, Capu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chines and Ieſuites, to bee daily ſent abroade from him, as his Apoſtles and Prophets, to preach his newe Goſpelles, and that newe Article of Faith, the extrauagant deuiſe of BONIFACE the eight, <hi>Vnam ſanctam Eccleſiam.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Vnam ſanctam Eccleſiam.</note>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:177893:7"/> And that it followes on neceſſitie of ſaluation, to ſubmit, and <note place="margin">Vnam ſanctam Eccleſiam.</note> obey the Pope in all things, holding and obſeruing his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances as heauenly. <hi>C. ſic omnes. Diſt.</hi> 19. And ſay, that his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline <note place="margin">C. Sic omnes Diſt 19. C. Sors non eſt cauſ. 26. Quaeſt. 3. C. Honoratus Diſt. 74.</note> is more perfect, then the Goſpell practiſed and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Apoſtles, <hi>C. ſors non eſt cauſ. 26. Q.</hi> 3. Alſo, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell his vnderlings, to the obſeruation of his lawes, which hee prizeth more then the word of God, as it is to bee ſeene in <hi>C. honoratus Diſt.</hi> 74. And for the tranſgreſſion of his lawes and commandements, to be burned aliue, as we haue ſeene many, for eating fleſh on a day by him forbidden: but for blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the name of God, or whordome, there needs no more but a little holy water, one <hi>Pater noſter</hi> and one <hi>Aue Maria,</hi> to waſh away the guilt of that offence.</p>
            <p>Now by the cariage of himſelfe in this manner, hee cannot be Apoſtolique, as he vaunts of himſelfe, nor yet the ſucceſſour of Saint <hi>Peter:</hi> for doubtleſſe he ſits not in Saint <hi>Peters</hi> chaire, that neither holdeth nor confeſſeth the doctrine, preached by Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and the other Apoſtles, who neuer were Law-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers in the Church of God. <hi>For there is but one Law-giuer, which is God.</hi> But there haue beene Ambaſſadors and interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <note place="margin">Iames. 4. 12.</note> as Saint <hi>Paule</hi> inſtructeth vs, ſaying; <hi>That we may be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med as the miniſters of Chriſt, diſpenſers of the ſecrets of God.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 4. 1. 2.</note> And Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe, ſending his Apoſtles forthe to preach, ſaid vnto them; <hi>Goe and teach all nations, baptizing</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 28. 19. 30</note> 
               <hi>them in the name of the Father, and the Sonne, and the holie Ghoſt, teaching them to obſerue all things whatſoeuer I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded you.</hi> He gaue them then no power, to make newe lawes, as the Pope licenſeth his men to doe.</p>
            <p>I am not willing to extend this diſcourſe any further, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I knowe it hath alreadie beene amply entreated on, by verie learned men of theſe times: but will conclude, that ſince he is not obedient to the Goſpell, but puts in place thereof o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doctrines and Goſpels, that he can bee no other, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen hee of whome ſaint <hi>Paule</hi> foretolde, in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> and as hee is deſcribed by ſaint <hi>Iohn</hi> in his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocalipſe. And ſo conſequently, his Church, wherof he tearms himſelfe to be the ſpouſe and head, is not that Church, out of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:177893:7"/> which there is no ſaluation, and whereto are made ſuch grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous promiſes; but rather it is the true <hi>Babylon,</hi> out of which we are commanded to depart, if wee will not partake in her ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominations <note place="margin">Apoca. 18. 4.</note> and plagues.</p>
            <p>Which I haue done, according to my duety, and the deſire <note place="margin">Concerning himſelfe.</note> I haue of mine owne ſaluation, which is no where offered, but in the true Church: and that is it, which followeth her Spouſe whereſoeuer he goes, and heares his voice, and liſtens to no ſtrangers: that is to ſay, whatſoeuer is beſide the doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in canonicall Scripture. For we ought to hold him (who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer) accurſed, that ſhall preach any other Goſpell to vs, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as Saint <hi>Paule</hi> aduiſeth vs.</p>
            <p>And we ſay with TERTVLLIAN, to them of the Romiſh <note place="margin">Tertullian.</note> Church: <hi>That they muſt ſhew their doctrin, written in thoſe cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall bookes, or elſe let them expect that malediction to fal vpon their heads, due to ſuch as eyther adde or diminiſh from that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</hi> For as for other mens traditions, whereon their Church is grounded, and not vpon the Apoſtles foundation, nor the holy mountaines of ſacred Scriptures: thoſe traditions are falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called Apoſtolicall, as <hi>Nicephorus,</hi> whom they haue among <note place="margin">Nicephorus in lib. 12. C. 33. 34. &amp; 35.</note> them, doth plainely approue to them the contrarie, in his book the 12. C. 33. 34 &amp; 35.</p>
            <p>God open their eyes, by the illumination of his holy ſpirit, that they may ſee the brightneſſe of his Goſpell, to betake themſelues to the aforeſaide mountaines, whereon the true Church is builded, and to reforme their doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, which is to the contrary. Giue vs alſo his grace, to perſeuer in his ſacred vocation, to his glorie, and our owne ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Iohn Le Vager.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:177893:8"/>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:177893:8"/>
            <head>A CHRISTIAN DECLA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RATION, OF IOHN FORENT, HEER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore a religious Fryer of the order of the <hi>Carmelites, in the Couent of</hi> Morthemard, <hi>and</hi> Curate of <hi>Caſtell Luſac.</hi> Made publickly in the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>med Church of</hi> Poictiers, <hi>on Sunday the 9. of Iune.</hi> 1603.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>2. Cor. 6. 18.</bibl>
               <q>Come forth from among the Infidels, and ſeparate your ſelues, ſaith the Lood and touch no vncleane thing: And I will receiue you. And I will be a Father vnto you, and yee ſhall be my Sonnes and daughters, ſaith the Lord Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S all the ſtones that are to build one houſe, are not brought together in one inſtant; and they likewiſe, laide readie on a heape, will hardly ſerue for the conſtructure therof, til by good and skilfull workemen, they be diſpoſed and made meete, each one to ſerue in his due ranke or place: Euen ſo our Lord God, doth not gather his elect, of whome he buildeth and erecteth his Church, all at one inſtant time or ſeaſon, but according as his prouidence and predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation hath concluded in his eternal counſell, and purpoſed for acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhment therof, in &amp; at al times. He cals one while ſome, at other ſeaſons others, and day by day (by his bleſſed ſpirit)
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:177893:9"/> of rude and vnapt members, he faſhioneth and diſpoſeth them, to enter into the building of his ſacred Temple: whereof his dearely beloued ſonne is not onely the foundation, whereon it is builded, but alſo the maſter and corner ſtone, knitting to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether the two walles of the ſeuerall people, Iewes and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, into one ſole building, which is his true Church.</p>
            <p>It is now twelue yeares and more, ſince it pleaſed God to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne, to make mee liſten to his inward calling, which from one day to another he confirmed to mee by the ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, whereby continually hee ſolicited mee, to come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and enter into his celeſtial <hi>Sion.</hi> But vntil this inſtant, there enſued many repugnancies on mine owne behalfe, taking it not to be expedient for my ſaluation: for an infinite number of humane conſiderations, and vaine ſcruples oppoſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againſt my deſire, preſuming to counterchecke thoſe iuſt reaſons, which the ſpirit of God ſuggeſted to mee; and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen like dreadfull Gyants, or furious monſters, guarding the priſon gate wherein I was encloſed, gaue me many great ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions, and ſtill continued me in the terrible aſſaults, euen when I beſt hoped to eſcape away from them. But in the end, it pleaſed the mercy of him (who deigned to chuſe me among the number of his liuing ſtones, for entrance into the building of his ſanctuarie,) by little and little to free mee from thoſe feares, by aſſuring my courage, arming me with his grace, and furniſhing me with ſtones to beate downe the one, and with weapons to cut off the heades of the others. So that now (by the meanes of his ayde and fauour) I ſee mine enemies confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, my priſon doore opened, and the way laide wide open for mee, to enter into the houſe of my father. Further aſſuring me, that albeit I haue greatly prouoked his anger, in ſo long time of abuſing his graces for mine enlargement, and therefore I ſhewed my ſelfe the more vnworthy, to beare the title of his ſonne: yet that he is ſo pittifull, as he will be mooued in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion towards mee, and allow for acceptable, the repentance wherewith he hath touched my heart; and ſo, if not as a ſonne; yet to receiue me into his houſe as one of his ſeruants.</p>
            <p>For now I will take no more delight in thoſe ſpirituall bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelries:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:177893:9"/> the pure chaſtitie of his vndoubted Church hath inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and drawne me to her communion. I will now ſwallow no more of thoſe bitter-ſweete baites, which haue ſo long time abuſed my taſte, as now appeareth by this contrarie heauenly ſauour. I deſire in the company of the Children of God, to feede on liuing bread in the houſe of the Lord. The Onions, Leekes and Garlike of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> haue ſeemed moſt odious and ſtinking to me, ſince I taſted of the celeſtiall <hi>Manna,</hi> which the heauens haue rained downe vpon vs. Too long haue I ſuckt the putrified and venemous blood, iſſuing from the impure dugges of that cruell woman, made drunke with the bloode of the Martyres, <hi>Apoc. 17. 6.</hi> High time was it therefore, to reliſh now (hence forward) the ſweete milke, diſtilling from the pure pappes of our deareſt mother. Too long time hath the deadly cup of abhominations, deliuered daily abroad by that horrid ſtrumpet, beene ouerlauiſhly quaffed on: now therefore it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooueth the more carefully, to experiment the ſweete liquour of life, in the Cuppe preſented to vs by the modeſt ſpouſe of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Hauing then hitherto borne the heauie burden, which the tyranny of Antichriſte charged my ſhoulders withall, I holde it reaſonable, ſince it hath pleaſed God ſo gratiouſly to deliuer me: that all the reſt of my life ſhould be imployed thus, to lay my neck vnder the ſweete and pleaſing yoake, of the iuſt rule and gouernment, belonging to my legitimate and Soueraigne king.</p>
            <p>And my tongue alſo, which heretofore hath beene looſe, &amp; vnbound to blaſphemies, as alſo the preaching of dreames and lyes: ſhall henceforth doe his office, in ſinging the maruels of my God, to bleſſe his holie name, in the congregation of his Saints, to preach his worde, for the edification of his Church, (if it ſtand with his good pleaſure, to render mee worthy and capable thereof) and alſo to giue him thankes, for that it hath pleaſed him (after hee gaue me knowledge of his trueth) to deliuer me out of the denne of Lyons, &amp; lodge mee in the fold among his owne flocks. Moreouer, to craue pardon of him, for my hainous tranſgreſſions committed, in that ſince the time
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:177893:10"/> when hee gaue me a taſte of his truth, I ſtoode out like a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell to the light thereof, reſiſting the bleſſed Spirit, and defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ouer-long the time of my conuerſion.</p>
            <p>But to the end, that ſuch as haue hitherto heere held mee for a member of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> may not preiudicately conceiue, that I haue thence diſmembred or cut off my ſelfe lightly, and without a great reaſon or ſubiect: it is expedient, that I deliuer the principall cauſe which heerunto hath moued me, and that is nothing elſe but this ſole reaſon; <hi>That out of the Church of God there is no ſaluation.</hi> For euen as during the time of the Deluge, all thoſe men that found themſelues to bee out of <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke, were drowned: euen ſo, all they that are out of the Church ſhall periſh, and no one perſon ſhall obtaine the eternall inheritance, if firſt of all he haue not God for his Father, and there is no man can haue him for his Father, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he haue the Church for his Mother.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as the ſpirit of God hath giuen mee to knowe, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is not his Church, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this the true reformed Church: deſiring to bee ſaued, I haue quitted the one, to enter into the boſome of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>And although I can by many reaſons approue and cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewe, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is not the Church of God: yet for auoyding of prolixitie, I will produce but three onely, the verie leaſt whereof, is ſufficient to perſwade mee vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly, and all ſuch as are endued with the vnction which teacheth all thinges, that that Church can not any way bee it.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, that euery congregation which aboliſheth the commaundementes of God, to eſtabliſh other that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to them: doth (by this meanes) breake the affinitie which it had with God, and forſaking the ſame, can no way bee the Church of God. The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath abrogated or abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed the commaundements of God, and hath eſtabliſhed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers quite contrarie to them: by which meanes ſhe hath bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the band of alliance with God, and ſo forſaken God. It enſueth then, that it cannot be the Church of God.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:177893:10"/>
            <p>Now for better iuſtifying the minor of this argument, wee neede to regarde nothing elſe, but what God hath required of a Church, for approbation to bee his, by the two firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of the Lawe.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, he will bee knowne of her to bee God onely, and as ſuch a one to bee ſerued, honoured and adored, forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to haue any other Gods before him, or to giue them any part of his glorie. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 3.</p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath ſo farre failed in the keeping of this commaundement, as ſhee hath altogether practiſed the contrarie, receiuing an innumerable multitude of Gods, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of Saints by the Pope Canonized: which is as much to ſay, as Deified, and to them hath attributed and rendered, the ſelfe ſame honour, ſeruice and adoration, which onely ought for GOD to bee reſerued. For ſhee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uokes and calles vpon them, makes vowes to them, buildes Temples to them, erectes Altars, ordaines feaſtes, celebrates diuine honour and ſeruice to them; all which thinges doe appertaine to none but God onely. And ſhee is not conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to forge ſtraunge Gods in this maner, of the Saints ſoules, whome they beleeue to bee in heauen (although a great number of them, helde by her for Saintes, may bee buried in hell) but ſhee delves into the bowels of the earth, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens Sepulchers, where their ſuppoſed bodies are interred, to make her newe Gods of their bones, of their hayre, of their habites, and other ſuch like traſhe, which ſhee hath cauſed to bee enchaſed into golde and ſiluer, and ſo ſet v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Altares, or caried about on their ſhoulders in proceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and make the people to kiſſe them vpon their knees. Wherein aſſuredly ſhee hath exceeded the Iewes, who albeit they were maruellouſly enclined to the forging of ſtraunge Gods: yet were they neuer ſo brutiſh, as to canonize the holy Prophets, neither to giue any honour to the bones of deade men, for what ſanctitie ſoeuer they might haue beene com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended in their liues. Perhaps they builded goodly Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, to honour their memorie: but they neuer did any religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſeruice to them.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:177893:11"/>
            <p>The bones of <hi>Eliſeus</hi> might haue prophecied after his death; if by their touch a deade bodie had beene raiſed: yet all the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour done to them, was to couer them with earth, there to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waite the ſound of the Trumpet, when the ſoule which before had giuen life to them, ſhoulde returne againe to reinueſt them.</p>
            <p>If ſhe haue ſhowen her ſelfe impious and ridiculous, in theſe matters already recyted, then well may ſhe be iudged altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſenſeleſſe, in tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlating the diuinity into a morſel of bread, adoring it for Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; creating to her ſelfe daily a milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of new Gods.</p>
            <p>If ſhe haue thus tranſgreſſed againſt the firſt commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it will appeare ſhe hath carried no more reſpect to the ſecond, whereby God expreſſely forbiddeth the making of any grauen Image, or the reſemblance of any thing whatſoeuer, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aboue in heauen, heere belowe on the earth, or in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters vnderneath the earth; nay more, not to fall downe before them, or vſe any manner of ſeruice to them. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 4. 5. But this charge hath ſhe taken from the peoples remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and moſt maliciouſly hath cut it quite away from the number of the commandements, in the <hi>Houres,</hi> which is a booke of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, by her miniſters prouided for the vulgar ſort: and yet to the end, that there might ſtill remaine the full number of ten, they haue ſeuered the laſt, and made two of it. All her Temples hath ſhe filled, &amp; charged her Altars with the Images of men, of Diuelles, of horſes, of hogges, of dogges, and other reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blances, and to them hath made incenſings, offerings, ſet ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels burning before them, and her adherents haue proſtrated the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues before them. Nay, ſo ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gely hath ſhe herein procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that in the ſecond Counſell of <hi>Nice,</hi> ſhe cauſed it there to be abſolutely decreed, that theſe Images ſhould be adored, &amp; excommunicated al ſuch as did, or beleeued the contrarie, and that decree doth ſhee obſerue to this preſent day. Wherein a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth a contrarietie moſt manifeſt, betweene God, who forbiddeth flatly the adoration of Images, and the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that commaunds men to adore them. Now as ſhe doth excommunicate euery one that doth not worſhippe them, ſo
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:177893:11"/> on the other ſide, God curſeth all ſuch as doe ſo, or fall downe before them <hi>Deut.</hi> 27. 15. Let euery man then in this point be well aduiſed, which malediction ought moſt to be feared: ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that of God, or the other of the <hi>Romane</hi> Church. And though I ſhould conſider no other reaſon, to perſwade me that ſhe is not the true Church of God, yet this alone were more then ſufficient.</p>
            <p>But now another preſents it ſelfe before me, which is of no leſſe weight and ſubſtance, and that is it which Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith: <hi>Whoſoeuer tranſgreſſeth and abideth not in the doctrine of Chriſt, hath not God. He that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinueth in the doctrine of Chriſt, hee hath both the Father and the Sonne. If there come any to you, and bring not this doctrine, receiue him not into your houſe, neither bid him, God ſpeede. 2. Iohn. 9. 10.</hi> And Saint <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith: <hi>Though wee, or an Angell from Heauen doe preach vnto you otherwiſe, then that which wee haue preached vnto you, let him bee accurſed, &amp;c. Galat.</hi> 1. 8. 9. The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath not continued in the doctrine of Chriſt, but hath announced &amp; receiued another Goſpell, contrarie to that which the Apoſtles preached. Therefore ſhee hath not God, ſhee ought not to be receiued nor acknowledged, nor yet to be ſaluted, but held as execrable and accurſed. Wherefore then, if ſhe haue not God, ſhe is not the Church of God, euen no more then the bodie of a man, when the ſoule is ſeparated from it, can then be called, or ſaid to be a man. If alſo ſhe be accurſed, ſhe is not the Church of God, becauſe the Church of God is euermore bleſſed: and therefore whoſoeuer will bee ſaued, ought neceſſarily to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake her, and ranke himſelfe there where God abideth.</p>
            <p>It ſhall be eaſie for mee to approue the aſſumption of this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, by the conference of the doctrine of Ieſus Chriſt which the Apoſtles preached: with that which the Pope, and all his doctors and preachers Romaniſts, doe holde and preach in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and I wil begin at the very fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dation of the Church.</p>
            <p>The doctrine Apoſtolical teacheth, <hi>Other foundation can no man lay, then that which is laide, which is Ieſus Chriſt. 1. Cor.</hi> 3. 11. Whereupon, himſelfe was deſirous to build his Church,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:177893:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:177893:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:177893:13"/> ſaying: <hi>Vpon this Rock</hi> (which is Chriſt, the ſtone which the <hi>Romane</hi> builders haue aſwell refuſed, as the <hi>Iewes</hi> did) <hi>will I build my Church. Math.</hi> 16. 18. The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken her ſelfe from vnder this foundation, and will needes bee grounded on that of Saint <hi>Peter.</hi> But I referre to their opinion, who cannot bee ſo vnprouided of iudgement, how well the Church ſhould bee defended againſt the powers of hell, if ſhee had not a more ſolide foundation then that of Saint <hi>Peter:</hi> who at the voice of a ſilly young mayden, was in ſuch ſort ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, as all that was builded on him was neere hand ouerturned. If ſo weak a winde did totter that foundation, what then could the terrible ſtormes do, which Sathan and his Angels (which are the powers of the ayre) vented out of hell againſt the Church of God.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtles taught: <hi>That wee are ſaued and iuſtified freely by his grace, through the redemption that is in Chriſt Ieſus, by Faith in his bloud. Rom. 3. 24. 25. And not by workes, leaſt any man ſhould boaſt himſelfe. Epheſ.</hi> 2. 8. 9. which are the three cauſes of our iuſtification and ſaluation: the efficient whereof, is the grace or mercie of God: the materiall, is Ieſus Chriſt in his bloude: and the inſtrumentall, faith in him. The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth dogmatiſe the quite contrarie: that wee may acquire iuſtice and Paradiſe, by our good works, and be iuſtified before God by them.</p>
            <p>The doctrine Apoſtolicall teſtifieth: <hi>That by the bloude of Chriſt wee are redeemed. 1. Pet. 1. 19. Apoc. 5. 9. purged, Hebre. 1. 3. waſhed and cleanſed from all our ſinnes. Iohn. 1. 29. Apoc.</hi> 1. 6. The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> holdes, that wee may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme our ſinnes by almes, faſtings, pilgrimages, celebrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Maſſes, and ſuch like thinges. That there is another pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, beſide the bloud of Chriſt, whereby hee ſatiſfied to GOD, for the paines which were due vnto vs, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in wee are purged, cleanſed and waſhed from all ſoyle of ſinne, to appeare pure and vnpolluted before the face of God.</p>
            <p>The ſame doctrine of the Apoſtles, propoſeth vnto vs one ſole Mediatour, Aduocate and Interceſſour, betweene God &amp;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:177893:13"/> men, to gaine grace and remiſſion of their ſinnes, to wit, Ieſus Chriſt. 1. <hi>Tim. 2. 5. 1. Iohn. 2. 1.</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute this office to Saints.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtles taught, that before the comming of Ieſus Chriſt, there were many Prieſts or ſacrificers made, becauſe by death they were impeached from enduring, &amp; ſo ſucceeded one another. But Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>becauſe he endureth euer, hath an euerlaſting Prieſthode. Hebre. 7. 23. 24.</hi> and becauſe he had no neede of any ſucceſſour, therefore there was no neede alſo, to offer daily ſacrifices for ſinne. For he did it once for all, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering vp himſelfe, and by this oblation onely (the efficacie wherof is daily recent before God) he hath conſecrated, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuitie, thoſe that ſhal be ſaued. <hi>He. 9. 10.</hi> The Romane Church holds the Pope for ſoueraigne ſacrificer, as if Chriſt, to whom this office onely appertaineth, were dead, and he of neceſſitie ought to be his ſucceſſour. She acknowledgeth alſo, all the Prieſts of Popery, not only to be ſacrificers, whoſe office (ſhee faith) is daily to offer ſacrifice in the Maſſe, for the ſins of the liuing and of the dead: but likewiſe (O blaſphemie, aboue all blaſphemies the moſt execrable) ſhe cals them creatours of the Creator. <hi>Stella clericorum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtles deliuered teſtimonie, <hi>That Chriſt was the Prince of Paſtors, and Prince of the Kings vpon earth. 1. Pet. 5. 2. 4. Apoc. 1. 5.</hi> Attributing to him the ſoueraigne authoritie, as well ſpiritually ouer the Church, as temporally ouer the kingdomes vpon earth, expreſſely allowed and giuen him the Father, <hi>The heathen for thine inheritance, and all the ends of the earth for poſſeſſion. Pſal. 2. 8.</hi> himſelfe alſo declaring, when he was to aſcend vp into heauen, <hi>that all power is giuen vnto me, both in heauen and earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Church (ſo much as in her lyeth) deſpoyleth him of this authoritie, and giues it to the beaſt mounted vpon the earth, which repreſenteth the Pope, acknowledging him, <hi>to haue two hornes like vnto thoſe of the Lambe. Apoc. 13. 11.</hi> to wit, ſoueraigne authoritie ſpiritual ouer the Church, when ſhe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimeth him vniuerſall head of the Church, ſoueraigne high Prieſt, &amp; prince of Biſhops, receiuing the lawes &amp; ordinances
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:177893:14"/> proceeding from the Dragon, &amp; preferring them before thoſe of Ieſus Chriſt, who proceeded from the eternall Father. Shee hath alſo graunted him, ſoueraine authoritie temporall ouer the Kingdoms of the earth, in regard ſhe beleeueth, that it is in his power, to diſpoſſeſſe kings of their thrones, and to giue them to others: that all kings doe hold their Realmes, by faith and homage to the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that the Emperour, himſelfe ought not to be held as a lawfull Emperour, if hee be not firſt approued &amp; confirmed by the ſaid Sea, that he haue firſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged &amp; made ordinarie ſubmiſſions to the beaſt, adored him, and falling downe before his feete, kiſſed his Pantofle.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtles taught, <hi>That ſuch as prayed in a ſtrange tongue, not vnderſtanding the ſame, although they prayed in ſpirit, yet their intelligence was neuertheleſſe fruitleſſe. 1. Cor. 14. 13.</hi> The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> forbiddeth praying in the Church in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther language then in Latine, wherein the greater part of the people, and many of of the Prieſts themſelues, doe vnderſtand nothing, therefore their intelligence muſt of neceſſitie bee fruitleſſe.</p>
            <p>The doctrine Apoſtolical holdes, <hi>That mariage is honorable amongſt all, and the bed vndefiled, but whoremongers and adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers God will iudge. Heb. 13. 4.</hi> And that, <hi>To auoide fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, let euery man haue his wife, and let euery woman haue her own husband. 1. Cor. 7. 2. That the Biſhoppe ſhould be the huſband of one wife, and the Deacon likewiſe. 1. Tim, 3. 2. 8.</hi> Hee pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth them alſo <hi>Apoſtates from the faith, abuſers, lyers and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, as ſhall forbid mariage. 1. Tim. 4. 1. 2. 3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Romane</hi> doctrine ſaith, that mariage is pollution, appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and allowing the opinion of one of her Popes, <hi>Siricius,</hi> who qualifying the caſe in this maner, prohibited and forbad mariage to Biſhops, Prieſtes and Deacons, tolerating notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous whoredomes to the whole worlde, and permitting publick Stewes or Burdelles, that daily pay trybute therefore to the Pope.</p>
            <p>By all theſe Antitheſes, we may eaſily iudge the difference, that is betweene the doctrine of Chriſt, and that of the <hi>Romane</hi> Church: and by theſe meanes, diſcerning it to bee a Church
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:177893:14"/> without God, execrable and accurſed, thinke it meete, that all ſuch as woulde bee ſaued, ſhoulde ſeparate themſelues from it.</p>
            <p>Now after ſhee had thus tranſgreſſed againſt the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of God, and inſtituted others quite contrarie to them in their places. After ſhe hath renounced the doctrine of the Sonne of God, deliuered by his Apoſtles, and cauſed (in their ſteede) the traditions and conſtitutions of men, meerely oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to them all, to be wholly embraced and receiued: There then remained no more, but to make a breach of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which our Lord Ieſus did leaue to his Church, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme and ſeale (by them) in the hearts of the faithfull, the truth of his promiſes, and vnder the ſignes of viſible thinges, to exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite and giue them (intirely) all his beſt bleſſings.</p>
            <p>Now if ſhee ſhewed her ſelfe ſo audacious and bolde in the two former points, it will appeare, that ſhe hath declared her ſelfe no leſſe preſumptuous and headſtrong in this third. For ouer and aboue her annihilating the Sacraments, eſpecially that of the Lords Supper, aboliſhing the ſignes, without which it can be no Sacrament, three things being required in all Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; to wit, the word, the ſigne, and the thing ſignified: She hath contaminated and prophaned the ſame, by her additions or diminutions, She hath added to the water in Baptiſme, Salte, Spettle, Oyle and Creame, without any one worde of God to warrant the ſame. She hath cut off from the Laitie (as ſhe tearmes them) the Cup, the moitie of the Sacrament of the Supper, and which beſt repreſenteth vnto vs the death and paſſion of our Lord, which wee ought to remember, and the waſhing of our ſoules from ſinne, which we ought to ſeeke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp;c. contrarie to his owne expreſſe worde, that ſaith: <hi>Drink yee all of this.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now God hath moſt exactly enioyned vs, that wee ſhall haue care of fulfilling what he hath commaunded vs, and that we ſhall not be ſo bolde, as to adde any thing, or diminiſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing: this was not a temporall commaundement, giuen to the Iewes onely, for his enduring is eternall, and hee addreſſed the ſame to his Church, euen to the end of the worlde. If it
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:177893:15"/> were not lawfull to adde to, or omit any of the ceremonies or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by <hi>Moſes,</hi> concerning the eating of the Paſchal Lamb, which was one of the Sacraments to the Iewes: why ſhould it bee permitted now on the behalfe of our Sacraments? And, if any one that miſpriſed the Lawe of <hi>Moſes,</hi> dyed the death without any mercie: what farre worſe torments then doth hee deſerue, that ſhall treade the ſonne of God vnder his feete?</p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> tramples with her foule feete vpon him; when ſhee addeth to, and diminiſheth from his worde, when ſhe deſpiſeth his doctrine, and deliuers another; when ſhe prophanes his Sacraments; and when ſo enormouſly ſhee tranſgreſſeth the commaundements of God. It followes then, that ſhee is to expect moſt rigorous puniſhments: and ſuch as will not participate in her plagues, muſt keepe themſelues from partaking in her ſinnes, and, leaſt they bee infected, to quit themſelues of her in due time.</p>
            <p>I adiure then all thoſe, in whoſe ſoules reſides any ſparke of pietie, of zeale to the glorie of GOD, and of affection to their owne ſaluation: that they, weighing theſe reaſons, and not beleeuing euery ſpirit, but <hi>approuing the ſpirites, whether they bee of GOD or no, propoſe to themſelues, that many falſe Prophets are come into the world. 1. Iohn. 4. 1.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And foraſmuch, as by the ſacred Scripture, which is as a candle ſet vpon a candleſticke, to illuminate all thoſe that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the Lords houſe, (and whereby all falſities, Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, blaſphemies, hereſies, ſacriledges, abuſes, ſuperſtitions heerein alreadie ſpecified, and infinite other follies and groſſe abſurdities, which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in her crazed braine, voide of all wiſdome, yet after ſhee hath once infanted them, they are nouriſhed &amp; brought vp in ſo greate an eſtate, as they haue almoſt obſcured the true ſeruice of GOD, and euen very neere hand ſuffoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the whole doctrine of ſaluation) ſhee may bee eaſilieſt diſcouered: yet notwithſtanding ſhee hath beene ſo ſubtile, as to forbid the people the reading of them, knowing verie well, that if they bee read, the pot of Roſes would be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered, and all the world abandoning her, would ſende
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:177893:15"/> forth an open cry vpon her, as after an enraged wolfe, that hauing broken the pales of the Churches Parke, ſought to looſe and deſtroy the poore flock of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe, ſhee could not ſo cunningly prouide for her owne affaires, but GOD diſcouered her parts of ſhame, and laide open her abhominations to the whole worlde: for the light of his Goſpell now ſhining euery where, all the nookes and corners are wide open, and the maſque, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſhee ſhadowed her deformed countenance, hath beene rent off from her face, and there is no one (if hee bee not wilfully blinde) but may ſee and perceiue her tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitude.</p>
            <p>And yet for all this, beeing thus publikely knowne, quite contrarie to the imitation of all ſhameleſſe ſtrumpets, perceiuing they can no longer bee couered: yet ſhee hath caſt downe all ſhame, and contemning all whatſoeuer, ſuffereth her ſelfe to bee carried into the depth of all ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie.</p>
            <p>Shee is become like to her owne Images, that haue eyes, yet ſee nothing, eares, and heare nothing at all. Shee hath ſtopt her eares like the Adder, as not willing to heare the voice of her huſband, who called her to better vnderſtanding, by the admonitions of ſuch as bemoned her miſhappes, &amp; deſired her reconciliation. She hath altogither ſhut her eyes, becauſe ſhe would not ſee the light of trueth, taking nothing elſe more op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite againſt her hart, then the bright ſplendour thereof. Bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no way comparable to the noble Eagles, who looke with wide open eyes (without winking) vpon the glorious Sun: but rather reſembling Moules, that delight themſelues to dwel perpetually in the darke bowels of the earth, making no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count at all of the light. And although they haue no eyes whereby to diſcerne it, yet notwithſtanding are they ſuch e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies thereto: as the leaſte opening they feele, for ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of any of his beames, or the ayre that may yeelde ſome glimmering to them, makes them neuer ceaſe, vntil they be vnderneath a great maſſe of earth, that light may not any way haue paſſage to them.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:177893:16"/>
            <p>In like maner, when God hath pleaſed to make ſome ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, whereby to cauſe ſome penetrating or ſplendour of the faire beames of truthes cleare light into the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> yet in regard ſhe affecteth nothing more then dreames, wherin ſhe hath long time beene nouſled, and vſed them as a common habit, ſhe hath imployed all her earthly forces againſt it, that no way it may haue entrance to her. And perceiuing that to dart her thunder bolts of exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication, hath growen little to her auaile, ſhe makes her recourſe now, to execute her deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes by the power of kings, by murdring Canons, ſwordes, and Armes: ſhe hath practiſed al the rigours of the ciuil lawes, ſeruing her turne with baniſhments, proſcriptions, impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, libbitings, burnings, and other cruell inflictions. Shee hath oppoſed the decrees of her Popes, the traditions of her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, the Canons of her Councels, the headie opinions of her Schollers, with the fallacies of her Sophiſters. Shee hath not forgot, to ſet (as marching in her formoſt rankes) her venerable antiquitie, her innumerable multitude, her continued ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Paſtours, her inuented miracles, her precious ſanctitie of Reliques, her moſt holy ſplendour of Ceremonies, the beautie and ineſtimable riches of her veſſels and golden ornaments, &amp; the thundring noyſe of her belles, as alſo the maruellous buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of her churches: whereby ſhee makes herſelfe amiable to all ſuch, as are deaffe to his voice that cals them to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>All which things, are like ſo many cloudes gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to hinder by their thick darkneſſe, that the bright ſunne might not iuſtly ſhine among them: like ſo many heapes of earth, onely to ſuffocate and burie trueth in, if ſhe but offer to enter vpon them: or as ſo many illuſions, to make her affrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, if (of her owne nature) ſhe were any way fearefull. But al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit the ſunne doe tardie time a while, yet his ariſing ſurmou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thoſe cloudes, and a vehement winde diſperſeth them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade, a great floud of waters deſcending from heauen, quite beares away all thoſe heapes of earth, and the bright preſence of the Lord makes all thoſe feigned illuſions to vaniſh. And in deſpight of all the policies of Antichriſt, hee will enter, to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:177893:16"/> viſite them that deſire his companie, and to comfort them that mourne after him, and powerfully deliuer them out of the bloudie wolues fangs, that call vpon him for their helpe.</p>
            <p>God alſo (in the end) will puniſh the blaſphemies, which this ſtrumpet hath caſt forth againſt his glorie, the contempt of ſaluation by him freely offered, but by her moſt impudently reiected, and will reuenge the outrages, done by her to his cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen and faithfull; which alreadie he had executed, &amp; quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded her in the bottomleſſe depth, but that his mercie at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth the reſt of his elect, who like good corne, are mingled among the darnell: and to the end they may not periſh with the chaffe, and be caſt into the quenchleſſe fire, he will (in his good time) ſelect them into his Garner. For euen as while <hi>Lot</hi> was in <hi>Sodome,</hi> he deferred the puniſhment of the wicked: ſo, while one of his elect ſhall abide in the polluted Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> God (with ouer-great patience) will endure her abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, and day by day augment the light of his trueth.</p>
            <p>Which that hee may in his exceeding loue and mercie ſtill vouchſafe to doe, vpon my knees I hartily entreate of his diuine Maieſtie: And pray you all heere preſent, to beare teſtimonie of mine vnfained conuerſion, imploring alſo your continuall prayers, for my conſtant per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerance vnto my liues end.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <closer>
               <signed>Iohn Forent.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:177893:17"/>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:177893:17"/>
            <head>A DECLARATION AND PROFESSION PVBLICKLY made, in the reformed Church of <hi>Paris, gathered together at</hi> ABLON.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>BY MASTER DENIS BOVCHER, SOME<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time a Monke of the Order called Saint <hi>Frances,</hi> in the Couent of <hi>Noiſy,</hi> neere <hi>Paris.</hi> On Sonday the ſixt of <hi>Iuly 1603. of his conuerſion to the true Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolike Religion; and abiuration of the Popiſh errours, ſuperſtitions and Idolatries.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Maſters, it is no newe thing, neither ought it to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted ſtrange, to ſee &amp; heare rebellions and blaſphemies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, or perſecutions and hereſies againſt his Church and holy trueth: for ſuch matters haue held place, euer ſince the beginning and creation of the worlde, as the ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſufficiently doe teſtifie. The wicked ſpirit, ſhadowed with the Serpents skinne, would neuer ceaſe, till he had ſeduced and withdrawne our firſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, from their obedience to God and his commandements. <note place="margin">Geneſ. 3.</note> In the daies of <hi>Noah,</hi> who was at that time a great Patriarke and Prophet of GOD, as alſo an Heralde of his iuſtice, <note place="margin">Geneſ. 6.</note>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:177893:18"/> there aroſe ouerbold audacious Gyants, giuen to all filthineſſe and corruptions: wherby they fell to make war againſt God, and in ſuch ſort prouoked him, as they drewe his iuſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt all the inhabitants on earth, and the vniuerſall Deluge of waters, wherein all fleſh was drowned and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed.</p>
            <p>After the Deluge, <hi>Nimrod</hi> and his aſſociates, puffed vp alſo with an ambitious headſtrongneſſe, no way willing to depend <note place="margin">Gen. 10.</note> vpon God, were the firſt that eſtabliſhed tyranny and violent dominion in the world, and enterpriſed to ſignalize themſelues for pride, in building of the Tower of <hi>Babell:</hi> but God made a mockerie of them, and euen confounded them in their owne enterpriſe, by the confuſion of their languages.</p>
            <p>Wee ſee throughout the whole booke of <hi>Exodus,</hi> how God, (after hee had with long patience toward <hi>Pharaoh</hi> the king of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> ſhewed that he forgot not his people by him perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, nor yet his blaſphemies committed againſt his Maieſtie) in the end, by a ſtrong hand deliuered his people, drowning the ſaid <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and all his followers, in the waters of the red Sea. Many other ſtrangers did bandie themſelues againſt God, and likewiſe perſecuted his people, as the <hi>Chaldeans, Babilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, Perſians</hi> and other people, whome God (at length) did vtterly ruinate.</p>
            <p>Which examples doe declare vnto vs, that there is no power nor prudence, neither any counſell whatſoeuer, that can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile againſt the Lord our God. But when hee once awakens himſelfe (as after a profound ſleepe, to vſe the Prophets owne words) hee knowes how to reuenge himſelfe on thoſe that durſt lift vp themſelues before him, and oppoſe their weakneſſe againſt his glorie.</p>
            <p>The Hiſtories Eccleſiaſticall and prophane, as well auncient as moderne, giue vs aſſurance and proofe hereof, in many great and generall perſecutions, and other particuler occaſions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, raiſed vp by the Romane Emperours, with other great kings, Princes and Infidel Potentates, againſt God, his Church and ſacred trueth: wherein (neuertheleſſe) hee hath in the end ſhowne himſelfe moſt magnificently victorious, euen ouer all
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:177893:18"/> his enemies, protecting and defending all thoſe that put their truſt in him. Which alſo was the bleſſed aduertiſment and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured conſolation, that ſometimes our Lord Ieſus Chriſt gaue to his Apoſtles, when hee ſent them forth to preach his word, ſaying. <hi>I ſend yee forth as ſheepe and lambes among Wolues. Yee</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luk. 10.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall haue manie enemies, that ſhall put yee to much paine and trauaile in the world: But bee yee of good courage, for I haue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome the world.</hi> And further aſſurance of victorie hee gaue <note place="margin">Luk. 21.</note> them, by meanes of a mouth filled with wiſdome, which none ſhould be able to reſiſt or ſpeake againſt. Vndoubtedly then, it is a moſt extreame folly, for men to thruſt themſelues forward, or to enterpriſe any thing whatſoeuer againſt his wiſdom, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is euermore too ſtrong for them, and he will maintaine his right againſt all power whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>In this reſpect (my worthy &amp; iudicious Maſters) becauſe now daies it ſeemes, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is mightily aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, by the multitude of her ſuppoſts and falſe Paſtors, who in ſtead of the true heauenly foode, preſent nothing elſe but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous hearbes and falſe doctrines, therewith to feede the ſoules, of men: Although (I ſay) it appears, that this Synagogue of Sathan do daily beare vp ſaile, God ſparing and delaying his iudgements againſt her. Yet notwithſtanding, at length hee will let looſe the arrowes of his indignation and fierce anger, againſt her blaſphemies, ſo that ſhee ſhall no way be able to endure the weight of his diſpleaſure: but ſhall altogither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine confounded and ruined. Whereas on the contrary part, hee will defend, preſerue and encreaſe (day by day) his little flock, as we may perceiue, that many (being guided and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted by his holy ſpirit) haue forſaken the accurſed foulde of Popery, to ranck themſelues amongſt the members of his true Church.</p>
            <p>And heere (my maſters) I preſent my ſelfe before you, as one of them, who although I was one of the leaſt members of that great Popiſh bodie: yet did I not deſiſt from perſecuting to my vttermoſt, the true Church of our Sauiour, and the verity of his Goſpell, which I impugned by diuerſe hereſies, which I learned in the infectious Cloyſters of ſundry Monaſteries,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:177893:19"/> publickly preaching and pronouncing them, vnderſtanding and corrupting moſt vilely the holy Scriptures, arming and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing mine owne turne, with infinite other ſubornations, only to contradict the trueth withall. I did intirely oppoſe my ſelfe againſt that goodly and bright ſplendour, ſhining moſt glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in the word of God: And (to ſpeake truely) I made a ſpare of nothing, which I imagined might ſerue for mine owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation in the eſtate of lying. But yet at length, when God made me to know, that it was ouer-hard for me to kick againſt the prick, and that I had wilfully ſhut vp mine eyes before, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe I would not looke on the bright Sunne of iuſtice, which vouchſafeth to illuminate all the world, God then (I ſay) in mercie looking vpon mee, did let mee plainely perceiue, that I deſerued no leſſe chaſtiſement, then the verieſt wretch in the whole worlde. And, to the end I may make a more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular declaration of his grace beſtowed vpon mee, receiuing <note place="margin">Heb. 8.</note> and likewiſe deliuering to you a ſound ſubiect of him, to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all praiſe and thankes with mee to him therefore, as alſo on the other ſide, that mine example of entring now amongſt you, may the more reſoluedly confirmeyee in the trueth: I wil ſpeak and deliuer vnto yee in very fewe words, the grounds of thoſe cauſes, which moued and incited mee to forſake Antichriſtes <note place="margin">Gal. 3.</note> part of <hi>Rome,</hi> to followe the trueth of God, and ioyne my ſelfe to the bodie of his Church.</p>
            <p>Firſt of all, the word of God teacheth vs, that Ieſus Chriſt is our ſoueraigne Prophet, King and Prieſt, and that at one time onely, he offered vp himſelfe a ſacrifice to God, for vs who were vtterly loſt, the children of wrath, ſinne and death. That by one oblation onely hee hath ſanctified vs, &amp; bought vs from the curſe of the Lawe, euen when hee made himſelfe a curſe for vs. Now the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> confeſſeth, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit Ieſus Chriſt did die for vs: yet his death is not profitable to vs, except wee doe ſome good workes, to apply vnto our ſelues matter of merit thereby. As if hee had not offered vp himſelfe to his Father, but rather is to be offered vp by the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices and Doctours of the Lawe: And that his oblation is not meritorious only, except the ſame be daily reiterated in the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:177893:19"/> Maſſe, which (they ſay) is propitiatorie to God, both for the liuing and the dead. That Chriſt hath not throughly deliuered vs from the curſe of the Lawe, but that (to bee ſaued) we ought in our ſelues to accompliſh the Lawe. Wherein they contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict manifeſtly the ſacred Scriptures, and namely that place taught by ſaint <hi>Paule,</hi> in the ſecond Chapter of his Epiſtle to <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2. and other places.</note> the <hi>Epheſians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The holy Scriptures alſo doe enſtruct vs, that Ieſus Chriſt is the alone Mediatour betweene God and man, as alſo the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">1. Tim. 2. 1. Iohn. 2. Iohn. 10. Phil. 2. Coloſ. 1.</note> Aduocate and interceſſour. That hee is the good Sheepheard: that God hath ſubiected all things vnto him, and made him the head of his Church. The Pope, oppoſing himſelfe againſt all theſe, commaunds, that prayers muſt be made to he Saints and ſhee Saints, as mediatours betweene God and men, and in regard that they haue beene men, they haue the more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication with our nature, and are more enclined to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion of our miſeries, then Ieſus Chriſt. And yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, it is hee that ſaith: <hi>Come vnto mee all yee that are heauie laden, and I will eaſe you.</hi> Beſide, <hi>Whatſoeuer you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Math. 11. Iohn. 14.</note> 
               <hi>of the Father in my name, you ſhall obtaine it.</hi> The Pope auoucheth, that although Ieſus Chriſt bee the heade of the Church, yet (ſaith hee) that he himſelfe is the miniſteriall head thereof in earth, and that all things are as wel ſubiected to him, as vnto Chriſt. That all, whatſoeuer hee doth or ſaith, ought to be helde and reputed, as comming euen from God himſelfe. That in things which concerne Religion, he cannot erre: &amp; yet notwithſtanding, many Popes haue bin found to be heretikes, witneſſe <hi>Liberius, Marcellinus</hi> and others. Hee ſaith alſo, that his commaundements ought to bee executed equally with them belonging to God. In breefe, hee would make the world beleeue, that the Church of GOD is a monſter with two heades, before which (equally) all knees ought to bowe and bend.</p>
            <p>God did likewiſe expreſly forbid his people, and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to all men, to make any grauen Image, of any thing <note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> whatſoeuer, to vſe any ſeruice thereto, or fal downe before it. The Pope on the contrarie part, hee will haue Churches to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:177893:20"/> be filled with ſtatues, Images, Idols, and pictures: whereto in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſings and honours muſt be done, and before whome they muſt fall proſtrate, although they be vaine things, &amp; the works of mens hands.</p>
            <p>Finally, the holy Spirit doth aſſure vs, that the ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are diuinely inſpired, that they are apt to enſtruct, correct <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.</note> and conuince, and that they can make a man wiſe before God to ſaluation. The Pope and his partakers, taking themſelues to bee more wiſe then the holy Ghoſt, doe not onely ſay, that the ſacred Scriptures are obſcure, but alſo that they be inſufficient, and like vnto a ſword cutting with two edges. That they haue a noſe of wax, which heretikes forme after their owne plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and wherewith they ſerue their owne turne, to confirme their hereſies. Theſe are ſuch blaſphemies, as none but a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell durſt vtter: conſidering that Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe, in many places, doth authoriſe the holy Scriptures, referring all to their <note place="margin">Iohn. 5. Luke. 4.</note> ſubiectionhat ought men then to doe, but followe his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample in all things, which concerne religion, and the ſeruice of God?</p>
            <p>VVhich if they of Popiſhe ſpirit would doe, ſo many tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and humane doctrins ſhould not be ſeen, directly againſt the word of God: As is that of Purgatorie, prayer for the dead, Indulgences, vowes and pilgrimages, auricular confeſſion, and others, ſo full of ſuperſtitions and Idolatries; and neuer were heard ſo many blaſpemies. Namely, as when the title of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the holy Father, or of his holineſſe, which appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to none but God onely, is attributed and giuen to a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall man, a poore and miſerable ſinner. The Sacraments of the Church, which are but two, inſtituted by our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: are they not broken and prophaned, when we ſee them to bee augmented, and added vnto, with fiue other baſtard Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts? All which, hauing no inſtitution, commaundement or promiſe in the word of God: we cannot, neither ought wee to make any vſe of them.</p>
            <p>My maſters, theſe things, with many others, haue incited me to forſake the places where they are taught and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, to leaue the large and ſpacious way, which leadeth to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, <note place="margin">Mat. 7.</note>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:177893:20"/> to follow the hard and narrow path, full of thornes and afflictions, which conducteth men to our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, at the end whereof, vnſpeakable felicitie is found. I ſet downe my reſt then (the grace of God aſſiſting me) to imbrace with you the profeſſion of true Chriſtianitie, and therein purpoſe to liue and die. VVhich I ſweare, proteſt and promiſe before God, and all this holie aſſembly. And to renounce, as at this inſtant I haue renounced altogither, al the falſe doctrines, ſuperſtitions, and Idolatries of Poperie: namely, that falſe, counterfaite and blaſpheamous ſacrifice of the Maſſe, quite contrarie to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, death and paſſion of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. Vpon whom only I wil lay the foundation of my faith, and caſt Anker there, with vndoubted hope of life eternall and perpetuall bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. I pray God (with all my heart) to grant me grace heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and entreate you all my Maſters, according to your charitie, to bee helpefull heerein to mee with your holy praiers to him: To whome with the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt, bee all glorie and honour for euermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This preſent declaration was with a loude voice pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, in the preſence of the whole reformed Church of <hi>Paris,</hi> congregated at <hi>Ablon,</hi> after the end of the Sermon: On Sunday the ſixt day of this preſent moneth of <hi>Iuly,</hi> 1603. By me <hi>DENIS BOV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHER,</hi> and thus ſigned.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>D. Boucher.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:177893:21"/>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:177893:21"/>
            <head>A DECLARATION MADE BY MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter DANIELL DVSERT, a natiue of <hi>Cinte-gauelle neere to</hi> Tholouſe, <hi>and heretofore a Religious Fryer,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Order of Saint <hi>Frances.</hi> Contayning his abiura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Doctrine of the <hi>Romish</hi> Church, and his proteſtation to liue and dye in the Faith of the reformed Church. Made publickly by himſelfe, in the Church of <hi>Mello,</hi> the 22. day of December, 1603.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Render thanks to God, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo long time of wauering in faith, and plunging in the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of the <hi>Romane</hi> Church, being altogither led by the cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Doctours of that profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and brought into ſuch an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, as being wholly ſubiected vnder the power of the Prince of darkneſſe: hee hath yet at length (by the vertue and effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacie of his bleſſed ſpirit) giuen me to knowe, that the doctrine preached in the ſaid <hi>Romane</hi> Church, is as farre off from the true Euangelicall doctrine, as earth is from heauen, &amp; that ſuch as follow that track, are out of the way of their ſaluation. For proofe whereof, it is a matter moſt certaine, <hi>That out of Chriſts Church there is no ſaluation at all.</hi> Now, that is the Church of Chriſt, which heares his voice: therefore, ſince the voice of Chriſt (that is to ſay, his word) is not heard among them of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, it muſt needs follow, that they are neither of his Church, nor yet of his flock. And to ſhew apparantly, that the voice of Chriſt is not heard in the ſaide <hi>Romane</hi> Church, we will proceede in approuing the ſame, by the manifeſt Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis and oppoſition, which is betweene the <hi>Romiſh</hi> doctrine, and that of Chriſt, contained in the ſacred Scriptures.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:177893:22"/>
            <p>And firſt of all, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> teacheth, that the holy Scriptures doe not containe all the doctrine of our ſaluation. Which is quite contrarie to the Apoſtles inſtruction, who plainely ſaith: <hi>That hee had knowen the holy Scriptures of a childe, which are able to make wiſe vnto ſaluation, through the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3 15.</note> 
               <hi>faith which is in Ieſus Chriſt. For the whole Scripture is giuen by diuine inſpiration, and is profitable to teach, to conuince, to correct, and to inſtruct in righteouſneſſe. That the man of God</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Chap. eod., v 16. 17.</note> 
               <hi>may he abſolute, being made perfect vnto all good workes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> It appeareth then that they erre, in teaching, that, beſide the doctrine of holy Scripture, the traditions of men are neceſſarie to ſaluation. Directly contrary to our Lord &amp; Sauiours inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, where he ſaith: <hi>In vaine they worſhip me, teaching for doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Math. 15. 9.</note> 
               <hi>the traditions of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> They teach alſo, that the ſame Scriptures are ſo obſcure and doubtfull, as we cannot clearely gather the doctrine of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by them. Contrarie to Saint <hi>Peters</hi> ſpeaches, ſaying: <hi>Wee</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 2. 19.</note> 
               <hi>haue alſo a moſt ſure word of the Prophets, to the which yee do wel that yee take heed, as vnto a light that ſhineth in a darke place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> They ſay moreouer, that it is not lawfull for Lay men (as they vſe to call ſuch as are of other condition, then Eccleſiaſticall perſons) to reade or meditate in the holy Scriptures. Againſt the commandement of Chriſt, who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth all men generally in this manner: <hi>Search diligently the Scriptures, for in them yee thinke to haue eternall life, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 5. 39.</note> 
               <hi>they are they which teſtifie of mee.</hi> And Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> doth not hee addreſſe his Epiſtle to all ſortes of ages, ſaying: <hi>Little children, I write vnto you, becauſe your ſinnes are forgiuen yee for his</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Iohn. 2. 12. 13. 14.</note> 
               <hi>names ſake.</hi> Againe, <hi>I write vnto you Fathers, &amp;c.</hi> Alſo, <hi>I write vnto you young men, &amp;c.</hi> And then, <hi>I write vnto you, babes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Doe they not likewiſe teach, that it is not lawfull to reade the holy Scriptures, as alſo, not to pray, or cal vpon the name of God, but in the Latine tongue? and make a very ſtrict obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation thereof? And is not this contrarie to the ſpirit of God? ſpeaking thus by his bleſſed Apoſtle: <hi>I had rather in the church, to ſpeake fiue words with mine vnderſtanding, that I might alſo</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 14. 19.</note> 
               <hi>inſtruct others, then ten thouſand words in a ſtrange language.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:177893:22"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> In the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> they alſo teach, that ſome others (beſide Ieſus Chriſt) haue beene exempted from ſinne, but doe they not lye in ſo ſaying? when the Apoſtle, ſpeaks thus: <hi>Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as by one man ſinne entred into the world, and by ſin death,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5. 12.</note> 
               <hi>and ſo death went ouer all men, foraſmuch as all men haue ſinned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Beſide this, they maintaine, that man hath free will, as eaſily to ſaue himſelfe, as to periſh, contrary to the inſtruction of ſaint <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> ſaying: <hi>A man can receiue nothing, except it bee giuen him from heauen.</hi> And the Apoſtle alſo ſaith: <hi>It is GOD</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iohn 3. 27. Phil. 2. 13.</note> 
               <hi>which worketh in you, both the will and the deede, euen of his own good pleaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Moreouer, they erre greatly, teaching that our workes are meritorious to ſaluation before God, againſt that which the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaith: <hi>All our righteouſneſſe is like the filthy</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 64. 6.</note> 
               <hi>clouts of a menſtruous woman.</hi> And againſt that alſo which <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel</hi> ſaith: <hi>Wee doe not (O Lord) preſent our ſupplications before thee, for our owne righteouſneſſe, but for thy great tender mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dan. 9. 18.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Do not they likewiſe maintaine, that wee are iuſtified and ſaued by the workes of the Lawe, and not by faith, and the mercie of God onely? Contrarie to the Apoſtles wordes: <hi>By</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2. 8. 9.</note> 
               <hi>grace are yee ſaued through faith, and that not of your ſelues, it is the gift of God. Not of workes, leaſt any man ſhould boast him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</hi> Contrarie alſo to this to <hi>Timothie, That God hath ſaued vs, and called vs with an holy calling, not according to our works,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 1. 9.</note> 
               <hi>hut according to his owne purpoſe and grace, which was giuen to vs through Chriſt Ieſus, before the world was.</hi> Contrary like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <note place="margin">Rom. 3. 28.</note> to this to the <hi>Romanes: Therefore we conclude, that a man is iuſtified by faith, without the workes of the Lawe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> Is it not common ſpeach alſo, as well in their writings, as alſo in their preachings, that we ought to ſtand doubtful of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation? Contrarie to Saint <hi>Paule</hi> to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> ſaying: <hi>Let</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 4 16.</note> 
               <hi>vs goe boldly to the throne of grace, that we may receiue mercie, and finde grace to helpe in time of neede.</hi> Contrarie alſo to his writing to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> where he ſaith: <hi>For I am perſwaded, that neither death, nor life, nor Angels nor Principalities, nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 38. 39.</note>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:177893:23"/> 
               <hi>depth, nor any other creature ſhall be able to ſeparate vs from the loue of God, which is in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord.</hi> And contrarie alſo to his writing to the <hi>Corinthians: That God hath ſealed vs,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 1. 22.</note> 
               <hi>and hath giuen the earneſt of his ſpirit in our hearts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> Doe they not defend, and manifeſtly againſt the worde of God, thas we haue other Mediatours and Aduocates, then Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, to wit, both hee-Saints and ſhe-Saints? Contrarie to Saint <hi>Paule,</hi> writing thus: <hi>For there is one God, and one Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour betweene God and man, which is the man Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 2. 5.</note> Contrarie likewiſe to the Euangeliſt Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> in two ſeueral places of his Goſpell: <hi>Whatſoeuer yee ſhall aske the father in my</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 14. 13. Iohn. 16. 23.</note> 
               <hi>name, he will giue it vnto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> Thus falling from errour to errour, they ordaine &amp; appoint, that we muſt call vpon thoſe Saints, and declare to them our miſeries and neceſſities: which no man can do, but meerely in vaine, becauſe both he-Saints and ſhe-Saints can take no acknowledgement of our wants, according to the ſaying of the Prophet <hi>Eſay: Abraham is ignorant of vs, and Iacob knowes vs</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 63. 16.</note> 
               <hi>not: thou (O Lord) art our Father, and our Redeemer, thy name is for euer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> How doe they labour likewiſe, to perſwade the world, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the neceſſity of prayers for the dead, or thoſe faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſoules, which (they ſay) are encloſed in Purgatorie? directly contrary to our Lord and Sauiours owne words, as the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt ſets downe: <hi>VVhoſoeuer beleeueth in the Sonne ſhall not</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 3. 18.</note> 
               <hi>be condemned.</hi> And in the firſt Chapter of the ſame Goſpell: <hi>Verily verily I ſay vnto you, he that heareth my word, and belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 5. 24.</note> 
               <hi>in him that ſent mee, hath euerlaſting life, and ſhall not come into condemnation, but hath paſſed from death vnto life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> Continually they preach, that there is another kinde of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie, then that which is contained in the bloud onely of our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt. Quite contrarie to the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Apoſtle, writing thus: <hi>If we acknowledge our ſinnes, hee is faithfull and iuſt, to forgiue vs our ſinnes, and to cleanſe vs from all vnrighteouſneſe.</hi> And as it followeth in the <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 1. 9.</note> ſecond Chapter of the ſame Epiſtle: <hi>We haue an Aduocat with the Father, to wit, Ieſus Chriſt the Iuſt. And hee is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 2. 1. 2.</note>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:177893:23"/> 
               <hi>for our ſinnes, and not for ours onely, but alſo for the ſinnes of the whole world.</hi> Why then it is moſt falſe, that there is a third place, beſide Paradiſe and hel, where the ſoules of the faithfull, departing from this world, are to be tormented, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they can be brought to heauen. Contrarie to the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> who ſaith: <hi>The iuſt man dying, enters into peace and reſt.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 57. 1. 2.</note> And in the wiſdome of <hi>Salomon,</hi> it is written: <hi>The ſoules of the righteous are in the hand of God, &amp; no torment ſhall touch them.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Sapi. 3. 1.</note> Alſo ſaint <hi>Iohn</hi> the diuine, ſaith in the Apocalipſe: <hi>Bleſſed are</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 14. 13.</note> 
               <hi>the dead, which hereafter die in the Lord. Euen ſo ſaith the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, for they reſt from their labours, and their workes follow them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> In like manner they teach, that to obtaine remiſſion of our ſinnes, we muſt make an account of them, and number all our ſinnes in auricular confeſſion: by which helliſh cordes, they ſtrangle the conſcience, binding it to impoſſible things. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſaying of the Prophet <hi>Dauid: That his ſinnes ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 40. 12.</note> 
               <hi>in number, the haires of his head.</hi> Again he ſaith: <hi>Who can vnderſtand all his faults? cleanſe me (O Lord) from my ſecret</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſalm, 19. 12.</note> 
               <hi>faults.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> Yet not thus contented, they teach beſide, that by the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our bodies puniſhments, and contritions, we may gain remiſſion of our ſins, &amp; life euerlaſting. Againſt that which S. <hi>Paule</hi> writeth to the <hi>Romans: For I count that the afflictions of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 18.</note> 
               <hi>this preſent time, are not worthy of the glory, which ſhal be reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> They erre alſo, in teaching the ſuperſtitious obſeruation of certaine daies, contrarie to the reprehenſion, made by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle to the <hi>Galathians,</hi> ſaying: <hi>Ye obſerue daies, and moneths,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Galat. 4. 10.</note> 
               <hi>and times and years.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> And a mighty abuſe they commit, teaching the ſuperſtitious diſtinguiſhing of meats, diſagreeing with the Apoſtles doctrin to the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> where he ſaith: <hi>Let no man condemne you in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Coloſ. 2. 16.</note> 
               <hi>meat, or drinke, or in reſpect of an holy day, or of the new Moone, or of the Sabaoth daies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> They deceiue themſelues alſo, in forbidding mariage to Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall perſons, contrarie to that which the ſpirit of God ſpeakes, without exception of age, degree or condicion
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:177893:24"/> whatſoeuer, ſaying: <hi>Mariage is honorable among all, and the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13. 4.</note> 
               <hi>bed vndefiled: but whoremongers and adulterers God will iudge.</hi> And this we adde hereto of the Apoſtle: <hi>Now the ſpirit ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth euidently, that in the latter daies, ſome ſhall depart from the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 4. 1. 2. 3.</note> 
               <hi>faith, and ſhall giue heede vnto ſpirits of errour, and doctrines of diuels: Which ſpeake lyes through hypocriſie, and haue their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences ſeared with an hote Iron: Forbidding to marrie, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding to abſtaine from meats.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> They pile errour vpon errour, teaching that there are ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Sacraments in the Church. For it is moſt certaine, that in regard the Sacraments are Seals of the mercies of God to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation: it neceſſarily enſueth, that none other can giue vs or promiſe vs ſaluation, neither doth it appertaine to any, but to God onely, to ſeale vs the ſame promiſe, which he hath ratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to vs by thoſe ſpeciall ſeales. Wherefore, hauing none other but Baptiſme, and the Supper of our Lord, to confirme &amp; ſeale ſo great a benefit vnto vs: it followes in meere iuſtice, that we ought to acknowledge none but theſe two onely, for Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. And not to make any addition to them, of Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Mariage, Penance, Orders and extreame vnction: conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, that theſe things, hauing no viſible ſigne of Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, neither any promiſe annexed to them of eternall ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (which are the eſſentiall conditions of Sacraments) cannot be reckoned to be any ſuch.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> And how ridiculous likewiſe doe they ſhewe themſelues when they teach, that the vertue &amp; efficacie of the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts doth depend vpon the intention of him that is to adminiſter them? when as (quite contrarie) the power and ſtrength of them, depends only vpon the ordinance of God, &amp; on the faith of him that is to vſe them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> Moreouer, their inſtruction alſo is very erronious, that the pretended Sacraments of Confirmation, and of the Orders Ec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall, are more worthy and excellent, then either Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, or the Lords Supper. Becauſe (ſay they) that by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation &amp; Orders, the indclible, or neuer to be razed out Cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>racter (as they call it) is thereby imprinted in the ſoules of them that receiue them. And likewiſe, becauſe they are admin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtred
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:177893:24"/> by perſons much more excellent, to wit, by Biſhops only: whereas both Baptiſme, and the holy Supper, doe imprint no Character at all, and may be miniſtred by ſimple Prieſts.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/> Ouer and beyond all theſe, they teach, that the bodie and bloud of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained vnder theſe kinds, that is to ſay, the accidents of Bread and Wine, contrarie to the Article of our faith, which ſaith: <hi>That Chriſt ſhall not deſcende at all from heauen, but when he comes at the latter day, to iudge both the quicke and the deade.</hi> And contrarie to that which <hi>S. Peter</hi> ſaith in the Actes of the Apoſtles: <hi>That the heauens muſt containe him, vntill the time that all things be reſtored.</hi> But by <note place="margin">Act. 3. 21.</note> this doctrine, they will haue Ieſus Chriſt to be encloſed vnder the natures of Bread and Wine, and make him thereby inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, impalpable, and filling many places at one and the ſame inſtant, whereby they rob him of his humane nature, wherein (ſinne onely excepted) hee was made in all thinges like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24"/> On the other ſide, taking away vniuſtly from the Lay people, to wit, ſuch as are not Eccleſiaſticall perſons, the Cup of the Lord, which hee proteſted to bee the newe Teſtament in his bloud, ſhed for the remiſſion of many: goe they not againſt the vniuerſall commaundement of Ieſus Chriſt, where he ſaith: <hi>Drinke yee all of it?</hi> and do they not thus violate the teſtamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie <note place="margin">Math. 26. 27.</note> inſtitution of the Sonne of God?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/> But the errour of errours, thruſt into this Sacrament, is, when they teach, that in the Euchariſt in their Maſſe, there is a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice <note place="margin">Heb. 9. 25. 26.</note> expiatorie, for the liuing and for the deade; Ieſus Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing euery day crucified againe, infinite times, by the hands of the Prieſt. Contrarie to that of the Apoſtle, in the <hi>Hebrewes: Not that he ſhould offer himſelfe often, as the high Prieſt entred into the Holy place, euery yeare with other bloude. For then muſt he haue often ſuffered ſince the foundation of the world: But now in the end of the world, hath hee appeared once, to put away ſinne, by the ſacrifice of himſelfe.</hi> And in the tenth of the ſame E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, hee ſaith: <hi>Loe, I come to doe thy will, O God. By the which</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10. 9. 10.</note> 
               <hi>will wee are ſanctified, euen by the offering of the bodie of Ieſus Chriſt once made.</hi> Whereby we learne, that the ſacrifice which
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:177893:25"/> our Lord Ieſus once onely offered, is alone ſufficient, ſoly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and of perpetuall continuance to expiate our ſinnes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any reiterating or renewing: as hauing no imperfection whatſoeuer, neither can (by length or ſucceſſion of times) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come fruitleſſe or vnprofitable: as they would gladly make vs beleeue, who, according to their owne doctrine, doe daily cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie the Lord anew.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="26"/> And what nature can but iuſtly complaine, when they main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that we ought to fall downe and proſtrate our ſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Images? contrary to the ſecond commandement, giuen by God himſelfe: <hi>Thou ſhalt make thee no grauen Image &amp;c. Thou ſhalt not bow downe to them, neither ſerue them, &amp;c.</hi> But aboue <note place="margin">Exod. 20. 4. 5.</note> all, he that hath any care at al, of the glorie of his Lord and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, cannot but feele himſelfe ſtirred with holy zeale, when he lookes into their ouerdaring boldneſſe, that they durſt and yet dare, cut quite away the ſecond Commandement, from the Lawe of the Soueraigne Creatour both of Heauen &amp; earth.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="27"/> In briefe, ſince in the <hi>Romane</hi> Church, vnder the Popes au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, ſo many errours are defended and maintained (both by fire and bloud) againſt God, his holy word and commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, and (beyond al other) againſt the merits and benefits, enſuing onely by our Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus: wee may ſeriouſly enter into conſideration, if he deſerue not truely to bee called, the man of ſinne, the ſonne of perdition, that oppoſeth and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth himſelfe, againſt all that is called God, or tendeth to his honour. <hi>For he ſitteth as God, in the Temple of God, ſhewing him ſelfe as if hee were God,</hi> as ſaint <hi>Paule</hi> writeth to the <hi>Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2. 4.</note> of him. For firſt of all they ſay: That he hath right aboue right, and beyond right, that he may diſpenſe againſt the foure <note place="margin">1. Dic. Non. dec de la Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe. Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. de. M. 12 2. Clement. 5. Clement. 3. Can. ſi papa. 4 In Conſtale Boniſ. Ex de Maior, et obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dien. S. 10. 6.</note> Euangeliſts, the Epiſtles of Saint <hi>Paule,</hi> and the foure firſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councels. Secondly, that he can command the Angels, to open and ſhut the heauens, to giue pardon for many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds and thouſands of yeares. Thirdly, that he hath a charter of condemning ſoules into hell. Fourthly, that he hath the two ſwords, temporall and ſpirituall, whereby hee may conferre of kingdomes and Eſtates: diſpenſe with ſubiectes oathes of fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie: commaund ouer kings and Emperours, and make them
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:177893:25"/> to fall before his feete. Is this any thing elſe, then to lift him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe aboue all that is called God, or that is worſhipped? So by conſequent, hee makes himſelfe no Lieutenant of Chriſt, who ſaide: <hi>That his kingdome was not of this world,</hi> and fled away <note place="margin">Luk. 19. 14.</note> when they would haue made him king. In briefe, is this the beeing of S. <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſor? who cared neither for gold nor ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, as he proteſteth of himſelfe in the Acts of the Apoſtles. <note place="margin">Act. 2. 45. 1. Pet. 5. 1. 2. 3 4.</note> And who prayed in all modeſtie the Elders: <hi>To feede the flocke of Chriſt. Not as if they were Lords ouer Gods heritage, but that they might be examples to the flocke. To the end, that when the chiefe ſheepeheard ſhall appeare, they might receiue an incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible crowne of glorie.</hi> It followes not (by his behauiour) that he ſhould be the Vicar of Chriſt, nor the ſucceſſour of Saint <hi>Peter:</hi> much leſſe then is he worthy, to ſit in the Temple of God, and make himſelfe honoured as a God.</p>
            <p>Therefore, before I conclude, addreſſing my ſelfe to you my Maſters of the <hi>Romane</hi> Church: Beholde heere the important motiues and grounds, which haue moued me, to forſake your ſaid Church, following the Lords commaundement, in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation: <hi>Goe out of Babilon, my people, that yee bee not parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 18. 4.</note> 
               <hi>of her ſinnes, and that yee receiue not of her plagues.</hi> And not (as I proteſt here before God) on any inconſtant humour doe I this, for affection to noueltie, for reuenge againſt any one of you, neither to auoide any puniſhment to bee inflicted on my ſelfe: as (in your own ſoules) you are my faithful witneſſes. Nor yet to procure any repoſe, or carnall liberty to my ſelfe: but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for giuing the glorie due to God, &amp; to attaine the ſaluation of mine owne ſoule. Praying to the Almighty, who hath deig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thus to viſite mee in his mercie, that it would pleaſe him to extend the ſame goodneſſe towardes you, and deliuer you out of that deadly ſinck of ignorance. And ſo, to him that is King of Kings, immortall, inuiſible, and our onely wiſe God, bee all honour and power aſcribed eternally. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>D. Duſert.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:177893:26"/>
            <p>WE, whoſe names are hereunder written, the Paſtour and Elders of the reformed Church of <hi>Mello</hi> in <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ictu,</hi> doe teſtifie, that this day, being the 22. day of <hi>December,</hi> 1603. Maſter <hi>Daniell Duſert,</hi> (a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue of <hi>Cincte-gauelle,</hi> in <hi>Languedoc,</hi> and heretofore a Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Fryer, of the Order of Saint <hi>Frances,</hi> called the Reformed Order in the Couent at <hi>Tholouſe)</hi> did come (of himſelfe) before vs, and declaring, that hee, hauing taken good notice of the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of the <hi>Romane</hi> Church, being contrarie to the conformitie vſed in the Church reformed, and the ſacred Scriptures, deſired that we would lend him a hand, to entertaine him among the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of that holy flock. Vpon this declaration made, we examined him on the principall Articles of true Religion, and finde in him, that he comes not any way polluted among vs, nor ſuffers himſelfe to be tranſported in in this his change, by giddie inconſtancie: nor ſeekes to exempt himſelfe from the auſterities, vſed in the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion he profeſſed before: nor yet to procure him any Licence to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall libertie. In breefe, he hopes not to attaine among vs, any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and treaſures of the world: Chriſt calling his followers here on earth, to the Communion of the Cup of his Croſſe, and his ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings. To theſe proteſtations, he hath added withall, that hee hath no other aime, but the quiet of his conſcience, and ſaluation of his ſoule. And after he had publickly made his abiuration of the doctrine of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, and ſolemnly proteſted, to liue and die in that of the Church reformed (according to the Articles before openly pronounced) we receiued him as a member thereof, and gaue him this preſent atteſtation, to ſtead him vpon any neede thereof. Giuen at <hi>Mello,</hi> the day and yeare aboue written.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>B. Manceau, Paſtour of the ſaide Church.</item>
                     <item>René de la Court, Eſquire, Lord of <hi>Boullay.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>D. Chollet, created at <hi>Mello.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Gracian, Lord of <hi>Vergne Nourry.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>P. Tauerneau. Elders.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:177893:26"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
